Welcome to poster 1083 “tedana multi-echo software and communal resources.
I’m Dan Handwerker and I’m representing the growing tedana community. Tedana has two main parts.
First, it’s an open source software that is designed to process and denoise multi-echo fMRI data.
Second, it’s a community and resources for people interested in multi-echo fMRI whether or not they use tedana.
The software is based on a multi-echo ICA approach that was initially developed by Prantik Kundu.
We have attempted to make that method more modular and understandable so members of our community, perhaps including you,
can better validate existing methods and develop better multi-echo fMRI tools.
A key addition in the past year has been an interactive reports page where users can examine each component that was accepted or rejected to better understand why.
The poster includes a static version of this report and here I am going to demonstrate the dynamic version
What you see up here is a pie chart of variance explained of each ICA component.
For each of these components you can see as I hover over it, it tells us some information about the component
We can see the same data as a scatter plot of kappa, which is a rough T2* weighting
versus rho, which is a rough S0 measure. Higher kappa and lower rho is typically considered signal that we want to keep.
and these are again sorted by rho values and kappa values.
What's dynamic about this report is that not only do you see this, I can click on one of these and you can see
this is a high variance rejected component. It's the linear drift of our signal.
This is the time series, the spatial map, and the frequency. So we can click on other rejected components
to get a sense of what's being rejected, and also click on accepted components to see what's being accepted
for example this is our highest kappa accepted component, and this looks like the response
from a task design with high visual cortex activity, and this is the frequency of that signal
so this is a very nice improvement because, when we get these results sometimes it's a little bit opaque of what's happening
so this is one more way of understanding what's happening, and better understand both
your own data, and, if you're interested, better try to figure out what
is or isn't working to both help yourself and us improve the method.
We do recognize that not everyone who is working with multi-echo fMRI can or wants to use tedana as a software.
In response to discussions at the last OHBM, we’ve greatly expanded the documentation on the tedana website
to include resources that may benefit the wider community.
In our documenation, you can see that we have the tedana pipeline, so we have all the stuff that's software specific
We have the pipeline. We have the API, which goes through every function.
But we've also added a lot of text on things like "What is multi-echo fMRI"
basic physics of it with links to things where you can read more
"Why would you want to use multi-echo", Considerations for when you're going to use it.
that might influence your decision. We've added resources of the different vendors
that includes sequences you can get for each vendor. How to think about what parameters to use.
"what parameters have been used in publications"
and finally, we have this section on good starting point articles, and videos, and lessons
if you want to learn more about multi-echo fMRI. Other people's software that uses multi-echo fMRI
and open data sets we're starting to collect and
and we've been trying to maintain a list of all publications that use multi-echo fMRI
If you use multi-echo fMRI, whether or not you use tedana software, we welcome contributions.
Particularly, if you have published a study with multi-echo fMRI, make sure we have it on our list of all multi-echo fMRI publications.
Thank you for taking the time to visit our poster and we welcome questions and contributions.